[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
last time we had started to discuss
charged particles moving in electric and
magnetic fields and how relativity
impacts uh the laws of charged particles
in electric and magnetic fields
how the lorence force law which is
basically the law of how electric and
magnetic fields influence charge
particles how that law and if that law
is really consistent with the principles
of
Relativity are the rules the same in
every reference frame and what are those
rules how do we have to
modify uh the non-relativistic laws of
motion in order to make them the same in
every reference frame and we do have to
modify them there's no question of that
FAL
ma uh makes good sense in a world where
acceleration is an invariant and in
Galileo's world or in Newton's world
everybody would agree about the
acceleration of an object everybody
would agree about the force on an object
everybody would agree about the mass and
so fals ma was a invariant equation that
all observers would agree on but uh
there are kinematic changes what we mean
by velocity what we mean by acceleration
and so forth and so it's not
surprising that the Newtonian Laws of
Motion will have to be
modified now in particular we're going
to have to understand the concept of
force and where forces well not so much
where forces come from but uh but the
deeper concept of force there are many
different kinds of forces in nature and
they tend to have different
extensions uh from non- relativist
non-relativistic to relativistic physics
for example the laws of motion of
charged particles look off in if you
ignore completely magnetic effects
magnetic effects incidentally are
themselves relativistic effects if the
speed of light were infinite there would
be no magnetic force on charged
particles that's because the force on
charged particles is proportional to the
velocity and whenever you see a velocity
you always know really it's a velocity
divided by the by the speed of light um
there would be no magnetic forces if the
speed of light were
infinite there would only be electric
forces and the force laws FAL ma
together with uh the Newton Law of force
the Newton Law of force looks
suspiciously like the kulum law instead
of products of charges we have products
of masses they both inverse Square laws
the laws of motion for gravitation and
for uh electricity electric uh forces
look very very
similar you might expect that perhaps
the generalization to the special theory
of relativity would also look very
similar and you'd be wrong they're very
very different in fact as I'm sure you
know the laws of gravitation don't
naturally lend themselves to a extension
in the special theory of relativity it
was necessary to go on to a more
thorough uh modification of SpaceTime
for gravitation but not so for
electrical forces So today we're going
to go through the
basic uh laws of
electrical and magnetic forces on
charged particles and the equations of
motion let me just write down what they
are what as lorence would have written
them
down just
before a few years before the discovery
of the special theory of relativity he
of course would have used Newton's
forces and he would have said mass times
acceleration this is when he wasn't
thinking so hard about the speed of
light when he was trying to be fairly
conventional about
electrodynamics what he said of course
was force equals mass time acceleration
by acceleration he meant exactly what
Newton meant by acceleration the time
derivative of the velocity and by the
velocity he meant the time derivative of
the
position all right let's uh let's uh
work on the left hand side of this
equation just for a moment mass is mass
acceleration is the time
derivative of the Velocity so let's
write time derivative of velocity both
are vectors ordinary three-dimensional
vectors I won't bother indicating that
they're both three-dimensional vectors
and the mass of every object is time
independent the mass is simply a
parameter that's identified with a
object once and for all it doesn't
change with time in relativity Theory
the mass doesn't change with time
because by definition it's the mass when
the object is at
rest in Newtonian physics it's a deeper
principle in neonian physics that mass
doesn't change but in any case Mass
doesn't change with time and so you can
bring it inside the derivative and you
can write the right hand side here as
the time
derivative of the mass times the
velocity and the mass times velocity is
known as
momentum always carries the symbol p
it's also a vector and so we always
write the right hand side here as the
time rate of of
change I'll put a little Vector symbol
on it now DP by
DT and that's equal to
force that's a fairly general definition
of
force it actually transcends a little
bit simple Newtonian physics as we'll
see there's a version of it in general
relativity sorry in special relativity
even in general
relativity uh that the time rate of
change is uh uh the force but there's a
slight difference in the definition or
the connection between momentum and
velocity in the special theory of
relativity and in Newtonian physics I'll
just remind you in both cases the
momentum is mass times velocity but in
the special theory of relativity it's
not ordinary velocity but the time rate
of change of position with respect to
proper time proper velocity
we'll come back to that we'll come back
to that that's the left hand side
actually it's the right hand side of
this equation but now I'm going to put
another right hand side to the right of
this I'm going to write down the lorence
force law we're going to work here's
your homework your homework is to put
all the speeds of light back into the
equations by doing dimensional
analysis we are going to set c equal to
the non-relativistic limit in this case
will not be the limit in which C goes to
Infinity C is just one it's the limit in
which the velocity gets very very
small so if you want to think about what
non-relativistic physics means it means
very small
velocity all right what's the right hand
side here well according to
lorence the right hand side is
proportional to the electric charge now
we're talking about electric and
magnetic uh electric and magnetic forces
proportional to the electric charge
which I'll call Q of an object and then
there's one term which is electric field
the electric field is a vector in
general it POS it depends on position as
well as
time it has a set of components the
components are three-dimensional
components X Y and Z and then lorence
discovered another term it was actually
implicit in Maxwell's work it was
implicit in Faraday's work but lorence
really spelled it
out
and it's the
velocity the ordinary velocity cross
product that I'm going to explain that
in a minute cross product with the
momentum oh sorry not momentum B thank
you B cross product with the magnetic
field the magnetic field also being an
object with components it's also a
vector in space very much like the
electric field but it influences objects
in a different way be of also position
and
time so in general these fields are time
dependent and position dependent
okay now the magnetic field I've written
I've told you that it's a vector first
of all I have told you what cross
product means so let's and most of
course most of you know what cross
product is but I want to think about it
in a slightly different way uh than the
usual concept of cross product the cross
product of two vectors you normally
think of is another vector and that
other Vector is perpendicular to both to
the vectors which are being multiplied
and proportional to the product of their
magnitudes times the sign of the angle
between them that's not the way I'm
going to think about the cross product
I'm going to use a definition of the
cross product in which the cross product
is really a
tensor it's an anti-symmetric tensor
that you make up out of two vectors now
it's very easy to make up a tensor out
of two vectors if I have two vectors A
and B and right now B is not the
magnetic field I just need two letters
so I'm going to call them A and
B if we have two vectors
I guess I should indicate that they are
three-dimensional vectors by a little
arrow over them ordinary
threedimensional vectors there's a
notion of cross product which itself is
another Vector which I can call
C right there's another concept as I
said of cross product which makes it an
anti-symmetric
tensor here's the idea you take any two
vectors and you can make a tensor out of
it a tensor is simply an object with two
IND es instead of one now I'm thinking
now about threedimensional
space so a vector has three components a
tensor in this case has nine components
3 * 3 it's a matrix built up out of the
components of the vector so if the
vector a has three components
incidentally I will freely interchange
between one 2 and three and X Y and
Z so X is 1 Y is 2 Z is 3
a has three components B has three
components uh the cross product also has
three components but as we'll see in a
moment that's a leaves a little bit of
an ambiguity there are two objects in
three dimensions which have three
components one of them or three
independent components one of them is a
vector and the other is an
anti-symmetric
tensor so given two vectors we can
always make a tensor for example we can
make the tensor a m m and n remember mu
and
new go
from 0 to
three time and
space that's the notation I will use
I've been using things from the rear end
of the Greek alphabet represent
space-time indices M's and n's Latin
letters just go from one to 1 to three
ordinary space ordinary spatial indices
all right so if you like a four Vector
has an index m one 2 and three and also
a fourth index
zero okay so am we're working now
strictly in three dimensions trying to
get three dimensional space and ordinary
vectors right a we can take a m *
BN that is a matrix whose components if
we wanted to work out the components
the 1 one component would be A1
B1 the one two component over here would
be A1 B2 and then A1 B3 I won't write
them all out but here would be A2
B1 A2 B2 and so
forth nine components alog together nine
independent components now as it stands
this is not an anti-symmetric tensor
it's it's got no particular
symmetry there's no particular symmetry
A2 B1 is not there's no particular
reason why A2 B1 should be the same as
A1
B2 they're two quite different things
but if we
subtract an
nbm in other words we consider the
tensor made by interchange in a and b a
m BN and a n b m if we subtract them
then that gets rid of all the diagonal
elements A1 B1 minus A1
B1 and it's anti-symmetric because it'll
contain things like A1 B2 minus A2
B1 in the One Two element you can see
that it's anti- symmetric if you
interchange n and M if interchange rows
and
columns the uh the two terms will
interchange and so what we'll
get is an anti-symmetric tensor the
anti-symmetric tensor has zeros off the
diagonal right it has for example in
place over here not A1 B2 but A1 B2
minus A2 B1 let's make it a little
bigger
A1 B2 minus A2
B1 and then A1
B3 minus A3
B1
zero let's not let's we'll come back to
that over there uh then down here let's
see that's A1 what will we have here
um
A2
B3 minus a a 3
B2 and then
zero the diagonal elements are
zero there's off diagonal elements here
and what about the elements below the
diagonal the elements below the diagonal
are the same as the elements above the
diagonal except opposite in sign so over
here you'll have A2 B1 minus A1
B2 which is simp simply the negative of
Its
Reflection about the
diagonal that means there are three and
only three independent components of
this anti-symmetric
tensor well you can always put three
components and you can line them up and
call them the components of a vector
that doesn't mean that they transform
properly as a vector but these three
objects do transform properly as a
vector if we make the right
identifications in
particular those who know what a cross
product is will already see the pattern
that these are the components of the
cross product of A cross
B but in particular I'll tell you which
components they are they are the
components A1 B2 that's C3 Let's uh
let's uh write over here no let's just
let's do it over here
C3 this one is
C3 1 2
three all right what about this one what
would you put
here temporarily let's put C2
there and this one of course would be
C1 in other words these three objects
can be placed in one to one
correspondence uh with um with the
compon components of this anti-symmetric
tensor here the anti- symmetric tensor
is one form of the cross product which
in fact generalizes to other
dimensions in other dimensions an
anti-symmetric tensor will not have the
same number of components as a vector so
this is special to three
dimensions in higher Dimensions there's
no such thing as the cross product of
two vectors giving another Vector but
there always is the cross product giving
an anti symmetric tensor so the
generalization of the cross product to
other
dimensions is the anti-symmetric tensor
for three dimensions it's fine to think
of it as a vector now um it's actually
C2 here let's uh let's write let's write
it out here C3 is equal to A1
B2 minus A2
B1 now if we start cycling this equation
the trick is always to cycle through it
1 to two two to three and three back to
one C3 the next one what comes after one
3 one
C1 equals A2
B3 minus A3
B2 and one two one sorry three the next
one is two of course it's the only one
left all right and this is one two this
will be A3 23
B1 minus
23 A1 B3 I think
right okay now let's check all right
what do we have we have over here A1 B2
minus A2 B1 that's C3 I got that one
right okay C1 down here that's A2 B3
minus A3 B2 but C2 my temporary uh my um
my temporary
identification C2 as A1 B3 that's wrong
it's minus
C2 okay you can see there that C2 is not
A1 B3 minus A3 B1 but minus that so in
fact what goes here is minus
C2 so the components of a
vector can always be be displayed as an
anti- symmetric tensor or the anti-
symmetric tensor can only always be
displayed as a vector now what's going
on here what's the geometry of this an
anti- symmetric tensor has two indices
every component of it is associated with
two
axes an x- axis and a y- axis okay well
the XY axis the XY component of the
anti-symmetric tensor is simply
identified with the Z component of the
vector uh it's it's clear that it's
ambiguous do you describe a vector by
describing the plane that it's
perpendicular to in which case you're
describing it by a pair of vectors
namely the uh the pair of vectors that
defines a plane or do you describe it by
the arrow that's sticking out of the
plane the two ways of describing the
vector one by just an arrow sticking out
is describing it by its Vector
components the other way of describing
it is in term terms of the planes that
are perpendicular to those Vector
components and that's the description in
terms of the anti- symmetric tensor now
the the difficult thing it's not very
difficult it's rather easy is to prove
that the components of the
anti-symmetric tensor transform under
rotations according to the same rule as
the transformation properties of a
vector and they do they do so these are
two different aspects or two different
ways of thinking about
the three components of a vector in
three in three
dimensions the cross product and for
many reasons well for many purposes it's
smarter to think about the cross product
as a tensor rather than a vector but
then again in visualizing it and trying
to get a picture of it in your head you
might uh you might want to flip back and
forth between vector and anti- symmetric
tensor okay that's the idea of a cross
product now let's uh let me do one more
little exercise for
you yeah no not an exercise yet let's
come to the magnetic field now the
magnetic field is a vector but it is
also an anti- symmetric
tensor zero B12 B13
B21 which is minus B12 of course zero I
won't I won't bother writing the things
below the diagonal here it just get us
confused
zero and then B two three over
here the other ones are simply minus uh
the uh
these for reasons that are
historical for reasons that are
historical the components of the
anti-symmetric
tensor are related to the vector
components by an extra minus sign this
is not a cross product but uh it is just
a
definition this is equal to 0 0 Z
instead of B12 instead of B12 being B3
it's minus B3
then plus B2 over
here and minus B1 over
here it's just a a a semi-historical
glitch there's actually some uh some
better reason for it but of course if a
thing is a vector so is the minus of it
and so the connection between the anti-
symmetric tensor and the vector that
describes it is of course ambiguous
though I describe this plane here as
that vector or that Vector there's an
ambiguity once I fix that Vector we
usually fix it with a right- hand rule
uh A cross B C by making right-handed
coordinates but there was always an
ambiguity whether we identifi the tensor
with with the vector components or with
minus the vector components and for the
magnetic field as I said just as a
matter of History they were identified
with with minus the component
of the tensor in other
words uh the opposite rule okay so
that's the magnetic field can be
represented either as a vector or an
anti- symmetric
tensor what I want
to show you is an interesting little
theorem the force on a Charged particle
is V
crossb now we can write V crossb we can
write the components of the cross
product V crossb either by thinking of b
as a vector or a
tensor let me show you what happens in
the two cases let's work out the
components of let's work out the
components of V
crossb all right I'm only going to work
out the X component of it what's the X
component of V Cross or let's take the Z
component let's let's take the third
component of V
crossb Okay the third component of V
crossb
is by the definition of the cross
product where is it the definition of
the cross product the third component is
V1
B2 minus V2
B1
okay that's the third component we could
write down the others just by cycling
through I'm not going to cycle through
but now let's
use that identification up at the top of
the Blackboard to rewrite this notice
what B2 is it's also
B13 so this is also
the1
[Music]
B13 what about now there's
minus V2 and what what is
B1 B1 is minus
b23 minus b23 so that'll change a sign
here and it'll multiply it by
b23 so the component of v crossb in the
third direction is V1 B13 plus V2 b23
and I'm going to add in another
term V3 B
b33 why am I allowed to add that
in because b33 is zero b33 is zero it's
a diagonal term here and now we have
another way of expressing a very pretty
nice way of expressing the component the
components of V
crossb right we can cycle through it as
I said but we can also write it in the
following way V
crossb the m component of it m is 1 2 or
three notice the three here goes with
the second component of b in each case
here look at the structure of it in each
term you have the third component of the
vector being identified with the last
component of b all right so that
suggests that we should write down here
something B something M we should write
a
velocity but notice that the velocity
components match with the first
component of
b the velocity component matches with
the first component of b and so that
suggests that the answer is NM
VN now this means summed Over N so this
means V1 B1 M plus V2 B2 M plus V3 b3m
right repeated indices get summed
over that's kind of a nice uh easy way
to write V
crossb that's what it
is that's another way of writing the
Lorent Force law here if I write it out
in terms of
components then at least let's
concentrate on the magnetic piece of it
the MTH component of the
force evident then
is electric
charge
VN
bnm
okay keep that in keep that in
mind let me show you a little another
little mathematical fact about particles
moving in magnetic
fields let's get the electric field no
electric field for the moment just pure
magnetic field then there's a fact about
particles moving in magnetic field that
their speed doesn't change speed is the
magnitude of the Velocity magnitude of
velocity doesn't change in a magnetic
field that's because the uh uh the uh
the force is perpendicular to the
velocity but that let's let's see if we
can prove that let's see if we can prove
that the velocity not the velocity the
speed velocity means
Direction and magnitude but that the
magnitude of the Velocity doesn't change
in fact that as a consequence of that
the field varies in time oh if the field
varies in time yes yes yes yes yes a
static a static magnetic field yes that
that that's correct yeah the M subscript
on F over there corresponds to the m
subscript on the B right but you also
want the second subscript to denote it's
only the magnetic component we're
talking about this yeah what what
everything is three-dimensional there's
no electric component in here now but
I've set the electric field equal to
zero yeah I've set the electric field
equal to zero if there's a Time
dependent magnetic field the reason that
the velocity the speed changes because a
Time dependent magnetic field makes an
electric
field uh but uh let's just concentrate
on a Time independent simple situation
time independent magnetic
field uh we'll see I don't know as we go
along we'll find out if it was important
that it was time
independent all right so among other
things that means that the kinetic
energy of the particle doesn't change if
it's only in a static magnetic
field that means that the square of the
Velocity we can write that as VM VM the
square of the Velocity this is v1^2 +
v2^ 2 + V3 s or Betty at VX + B y^2 +
vz^ 2 this is the square of the
magnitude of the velocity and I'm
interested in finding
out whether that changes with time so
what I want to do I want to
differentiate it with respect to
time remember that I sum over repeated
index all right well what is this this
is just
twice the time derivative of
VM times VM
this is vm^ 2 the time derivative is
twice V is twice V time the time
derivative of V
right which
is twice the
acceleration twice the
acceleration
dotted with a velocity
now let's write the fact that the
acceleration we know what the
acceleration is the acceleration is just
the force divided by the
mass let's see what do we want to do
um yeah we want to substitute for the
acceleration I want to substitute uh the
force divided by the mass but in
particular I don't care about the
numerical coefficients this is going to
be proportional to
twice now velocity cross
B the MTH
component times
VM the acceleration in a magnetic field
is proportional to the velocity cross
the magnetic field the MTH component of
it times
VM but now let's use the formula that we
have where is it uh the formula that we
have for V crossb that I erase that darn
it I erased
it
uh
twice
B what is it b n
m anybody have it written down V crossb
the M component of it
what is it is isn't it VN BN m
v n BN M
right all right that's V crossb in the M
Direction but now let's multiply it by
VM so what do we have we have the
components of the tensor B
bracketed by the components of the
vector v on both sides
sides now the trick is to realize that
any expression like this is always zero
if B is
anti-symmetric for example there's going
to be a term which will be well let's
let's see what terms there are there
could be a term with V1 over here and V1
over here that will have to multiply b11
that's
zero let's try another term there'll be
a term V1 over here and V2 over here
that will multiply
B12 but then there will be a partner a
twin term that goes with it in which
this is two in which n is two and M is
one so that will be plus
V2
B21
V1 and now we use the fact that B21 and
b12 are opposite in sign equal and
opposite and this is also
zero
so if we take a anti-symmetric
tensor and we multiply it from both
sides on both of its indices by the same
Vector we always get zero the
consequence is that we proved that for a
magnetic field that d by DT of the
square of the Velocity is equal to
zero in other words that the square of
the Velocity is constant in time anybody
want me to go over that again
all right I just I I'll I'll just go
over very briefly again V MVM we
differentiated it and we got it
proportional to the product of the
acceleration times the velocity then I
used for the acceleration the Loren
Force law the magnetic piece of it of
course this would not be true
incidentally if there was electric field
only because if there's only magnetic
field then the acceleration is
proportional to V cross B I then use
that V cross B was vnm VN BN M
VM and then immediately from that it
follows immediately the symmetry of
vnm is um combines together with the
anti-symmetry of bnm to give zero now
why do I do it this way I could use
Elementary theorems about cross products
and so forth I do it this way because we
want to generalize it to four dimensions
where the Gen with the where the simple
theorems don't uh don't
generalize
okay so now we know some things oh
incidentally
well it's just true that of course that
an electric field will violate this if a
particle is at rest and starts at rest
the accelerate the um the electric field
will start to accelerate it and of of
course the velocity will not Remain the
speed won't remain constant it's only
because the velocity appears in
here in a particular special way that it
uh that it has this property that it
doesn't change the magnitude of the
Velocity I don't think in any place here
that I used the fact that the magnetic
field was constant in
time I don't think I
did uh what is true is a Time dependent
magnetic field will create an electric
field and the electric field will do
some
work all right now it's more or less
obvious that the electric
field and the magnetic field will get
mixed up with each other when you go
from frame to frame which are moving
with relative
velocity it's Rel it's fairly easy to
see this is under the assumption that
the laws of physics are the same in
every reference
frame it's more or less obvious that
if you have a pure magnetic field in one
frame then in other frames you will also
have an electric field in other words if
there's a pure magnetic field along some
axis and you're moving in some
direction uh depending on the direction
you're moving in you will see also an
electric field the way to see
that let's take a
case let's suppose there a magnetic
field in the up
direction
that I have a particle let's see let's
[Music]
um I have a particle which is
moving with velocity V we call this the
y direction the X Direction and this is
the third Direction the Z Direction one
two and three we have a magnetic field
in the y
direction we have a particle moving
along the X
Direction and of course in that case we
will have a force along the
z-axis V crossb will be along the z-axis
and there will be a force on that
particle along the z-axis now let's
imagine slow
velocities uh Newtonian physics when not
interested in relativity yet everything
is moving very slowly by comparison with
the speed of
light acceleration in Newtonian
kinematics is invariant so if one
Observer sees an acceleration a second
Observer will also see an acceleration
and the acceleration will be identical
as long as we're talking about observers
who are moving slowly relative to each
other all right now I haven't introduced
the second Observer yet I've only
introduced the fact that my particle is
moving along with velocity V but now I'm
going to introduce a second Observer the
second Observer also happens to be
moving along with velocity V and
therefore sees the particle at rest for
that Observer the particle has no
velocity but because acceleration is an
invariant under uh usual Newtonian
physics that Observer must also see an
acceleration for this particle there's
no velocity therefore the B field cannot
create any acceleration
momentarily momentarily at a at that
instant of time the acceleration is zero
in one frame it's zero in every frame so
as I move along with the particle I have
to blame the acceleration on something
else it cannot cannot be blamed on the
cross product of the velocity and the
magnetic field in fact we know there's a
force along the z-axis there's only one
place that that could be coming from
assuming that the lorence force law is
the same in every reference frame if
it's not coming from V cross B because
in my new frame V is zero it must be
coming from an electric field and so
there must be an electric field sticking
out of the Blackboard in the frame of
reference moving with the particle in
this particular case so in the original
frame of reference I started with no
electric
field but a particle moving with
velocity V in the second frame of
reference I have a particle at rest I
must have an electric field sticking out
of the Blackboard so the consequences
are that electric and magnetic fields
must mix up with each other under
velocity
Transformations but in order to get the
equations really relativistically
correct we're going to have to work with
four
vectors so let's remind ourselves about
four vectors and how the electric and
magnetic fields fit into four Vector
notation and then see if we can derive a
set of equations of motion which will be
the same in every reference
frame and as I
said we will have to mix up electric and
magnetic fields they will have to
transform we'll work out some of their
transformation properties I mean here we
did a little bit of it but we'll work it
out mathematically and see for example
that this does happen Okay uh we have
two Fields electric and magnetic that's
six components Al
together a second object which has six
components in fact the only object which
has I I said I say this all the time the
only
object in four-dimensional space which
has six components is an anti- symmetric
tensor now it's simply false you could
have six scalers you could have a vector
in two scalers I think that's all a
vector and two
scalers uh six scalers but though
neither of those are
interesting uh the other object which
has six independent components is the
anti-symmetric tensor so it's
natural it's it's natural since electric
and magnetic fields will transform into
each other to Guess that they fill out
an anti-symmetric tensor in four
dimensions so let's uh let's
here's the Matrix associated with it
let's uh just to guide my I I'm going to
divide it into 4 by
four and now my notation my notation
seems to differ from a lot of books my
notation is
always 0 1 2 3 No 1 two 3
Z that's because
I in my youth I used to call
04 now it's called zero well I'm not
that old that the but uh 1 two three 0
so 1 2 3 0 1 2 2 3 0 let's fill it in
with electric and magnetic
fields and some of this of course is
conventions some of this is rather
arbitrary convention what the invariant
fact is is that there's an antisymmetric
tensor that describes all of this
exactly how we uh fill in the components
is a little bit arbitrary not very but
we fill in the 1 two 3 the 3X3 Matrix
exact as we did with the magnetic field
before 0 0
minus
b z or
B3 I think this is plus
B2 minus
B1 so this part of it let me block it
out
the 3X3 part of it 1 two
3 is exactly just the magnetic field
tensor on the off
diagonal places over here we have the
electric field we have room for the
components of an electric field I think
it's
E1
E2
E3 the three components of the electric
field and of course in the lower spots
here we simply reverse the Sign Plus B3
for example down here we would have
minus E3
Etc anti- symmetric tensor six
independent components constituting the
um the electromagnetic field tensor why
do you use superscript oh as long as I'm
only in interested in uh in components 1
two and three as long as I'm labeling
things with 1 two and three it doesn't
matter if they're up or lower here I
simply mean you're right I uh I switch
notation up and down um pay no attention
to it let's see uh what would be
consistent I guess it would be
consistent to leave them as upper
components but it doesn't matter it's
the three components of the electric
field and the three components of the
magnetic field exactly as Maxwell and uh
Faraday would have Define them that's
what go into those places there so we
needn't pay much attention to where the
uh to where the indices are this is the
object made up out of exactly the same
fields that Maxwell and Faraday would
have defined and this whole object is
called f mu new it's an anti-symmetric
4x4
tensor mu and new run
from 0 to 4 to three or 3 to
zero and uh it is a 4x4 tensor it's
called called f I'm not sure why it's
called f I think maybe for Faraday but
I'm not
sure I don't think it was called f until
uh maybe minkowski I'm not
sure Einstein did not have that
notation he actually didn't think about
4x4 tensors what he simply worked out in
detail was the transformation properties
of the electric and magnetic field I
think it was manowski who first put them
together into a
tensor all right let's come now that's
that's our object that's our electric
and magnetic tensor it's a thing that
has to be responsible one way or another
for the force uncharged
particles now what we want to do is
study possible excuse me
possible Force laws that would be
appropriate in the special theory of
relativity so let's
begin with the idea of
acceleration we've already defined for
velocity for velocity U mu is equal to
DX
mu by not by DT but by
D okay
it has four
components um what are those four
components they are the four components
of ordinary velocity times gamma
gamma equal 1 / theare otk of 1us V ^
2 VX v y and
VZ time gamma
and then the last component is just
gamma another way to write them is DX by
DT DT by DT that's where the gamma comes
from the gamma is just DT by
DT okay so those are the four components
of four
velocity the momentum is M time U
mu that's P mu and the first three
components of it are the
ordinary momentum they are the momentum
but notice that they're made up out of
mass times proper
velocity that's what goes into
the generalization of Newton's
equations and it goes in not in the form
DP by DT but DP by
DT why because we want to make a four
Vector if
X is a four vector and too is a scalar
and too is a scalar or an invariant then
d x by the to is also a four Vector p is
a four vector and DP by DT is a four
Vector that's the left hand side in
other words it's entirely analogous
to what we place in Newton's equations
here except that it's D by D to instead
of d by DT okay we can write that if we
like well let's leave it this way for
the moment let's leave it this way we'll
uh we'll write it slightly different in
a little
while if the left hand side is a four
Vector the right hand side must also be
a four
Vector it's got to have the electric
charge in front of
it it is going to have the electric and
magnetic fields in
it let's see what kind of thing we can
invent we can invent something with no
let's let's let's for the moment just
call the right hand side F script F
mu F
mu okay now let me prove a little
theorem the theorem is that F mu here's
the here's the statement F
mu U mu is equal to to
zero now this is
analogous but not identical to it's
analogous to the statement that the
force due to a magnetic field is
perpendicular to the velocity that the
force due to the magnetic field is
perpendicular to the velocity it's
analogous to that it's a
four-dimensional version of it and we're
going to see now how it works how do we
prove
this we prove it not by using any
special form for f but by using the fact
which I probably mentioned last time if
I haven't I'll I'll review it well I
won't review it I'll do it U mu U
mu is equal to one did we do
that I think we did it's uh let me just
briefly remind you it just says that d x
mu by D
to DX mu U by D to is equal to
1 and all it really says is that well
this one one of these should be lower DX
mu all it really says is that the is
that the sum of the squares of these
differentials is just D to
squared okay I think we did that I think
we may have done it twice already U mu U
sub mu * mu super mu is equal to
one now let me differentiate that with
respect to towel if it's equal to one
that means it doesn't change along the
trajectory of the particle it's very
much a very analogous to the statement
that the speed doesn't change in a
magnetic field not the same thing
because there's four components here but
uh but it's mathematically analogous
let's differentiate it with respect to
toao all right we're going to get two
terms when I differentiate a product I
get one term from the derivative of the
first Factor times the second factor and
so forth so there will be for example du
mu times U super
mu and it will also be plus u
subm my M's and U's look the same don't
they I don't want them
to you
subm times d U super mu by DT by DT but
these are the same thing it doesn't
matter if you have when you put two
vectors together like this and some over
the indices it doesn't matter which one
has the upper index and which one has
the lower
index that's uh entirely uh no content
in that so this is really just twice
this what is this object this is twice
the proper acceleration times the proper
velocity okay this is the proper
acceleration
here and this is the proper
velocity the proper
acceleration of course is
proportional apart from a factor of mass
it's equal to DP mu by D to so this is
just m times the proper
acceleration right so what's on the left
here apart from a factor of m is d mu du
by D to and If I multiply it by U mu on
the right hand side it must be equal to
zero so it
follows it follows
that F mu * U sub mu must equal
zero oh did we didn't finish this I
should have said this is equal to zero
it's equal to zero because the right
hand side is just one and when you
differentiate one you just get zero the
right hand side is a constant when you
differentiate a constant you get zero
and what is the expression here it's
just proportional to the force times the
velocity what I wrote up here so you can
see that F mu * U mu must equal
zero this is a kinematic fact this
doesn't depend on anything it just just
depends on the definition of four
velocity for moment sorry for
acceleration for dimensional
acceleration and so forth and so it
tells us that in a four-dimensional
sense the force on an object must be
perpendicular or orthogonal to uh to the
four velocity in this sense that that
has to be equal to zero that means we
can't just stick in any old thing for
Force it's got to satisfy this
relationship here how do we satisfy it
well it's as I said quite similar to the
fact that the magnetic force is
proportional is uh perpendicular to
ordinary velocity we satisfied that by a
trick we made the trick of making the
magnetic field into a
tensor
MN and multiplying it by
VN this is V crossb
then when I dotted it into VM it was
automatically
zero exactly the same trick exactly the
same trick we take F
mu to be F mu new the antisymmetric
tensor times the four
velocity everybody know what I mean when
when I put a lower index on the four
velocity it just means lowering the
index by changing the sign of the space
components
right so if I
invent an anti- symmetric tensor to put
here and I multiply it by you
new guess what if I now multiply it by U
mu the answer will be zero
because f is anti-
symmetric let's just write it out
explicitly if the force is proportional
to F mu new time U new and I dot it into
U
mu the answer will be zero because f is
anti-symmetric so this is one way it's
only one way of satisfying the criteria
that the force is
that the force when multiplied by the
velocity is equal to zero is to build
the force out of an anti- symmetric
tensor fact it's the simplest
way well we have an anti- symmetric
tensor in fact we even call it f muu and
it's built up out of the electric and
magnetic fields so let's see let's take
this apart here is our equation let's
get rid of the intermediate step here
this is Q time F mu new
times you
new and let's look at this for slow
velocities first let's first look at it
for slow velocities we can um we can
study it for larger velocities later but
let's check that for low velocities this
really is the
um uh the lorence force law let's see
how it's related to lent Force law first
of all q that just goes for free that's
just the electric charge F mu new is
going to involve two terms electric and
magnetic and U has two kinds of terms
the time component and the space
components of U so let's work out some
example let's work out
DP which one did I work
out
yeah let's work out
DPX by
DT now the first thing is as long as we
moving slow I'm going to come back in a
little while and discuss what happens
when we're moving faster as long as
we're moving
slowly T and to are the
same for slow motion DT and D to are the
same so in the non-relativistic limit we
can just take this to be DP by DT as I
said we'll check we'll we'll do better
in a moment I just want to make sure
that for slow motion we have all the
right
things that's equal equ Al to Q okay now
let's see what we
have
uh mu and mu match here and here so this
has to be
FX and then new can be any one of four
terms any one of four uh uh four entries
there there's first of all FFX
XX
uux that's not there because FFX FXX
zero so this is gone then there's fxy
uy
plus F
XZ u
z plus
FX not or time you
not okay let's pull them apart what is
fx0 fx0
is electric field if one of the indices
is zero and the other
one is
space then this is just the electric
field so this here is we first of all
have a term which is Q times the
electric field they're both X components
so this is the X component of the
electric
field all right but what are these XY
and the XZ components those are magnetic
fields
so let's see what we have fxy that's F12
what is F12 F12 is minus
B3 so this will be
Q time
uy
B3 with a minus
sign and then from
here what is
fxz that's B2 no that's yes that's B2 so
this will be
plus
u u3
B2 you see what we're getting we're
getting the cross product of the
Velocity with the magnetic
field to the extent that we can say that
U is the same as V we've reproduced the
force law of
lorence EXC
V cross P plus Q * e you see where they
come
from
um let's be a little more
careful let's write let's write it more
carefully and not do the
non-relativistic limit let's do it more
carefully first of all we have DP mu by
DT that is DP mu by
DT times
gamma times DT by D DT by D let me just
write down what gamma is gamma is square
< TK of 1 - v^2 where V is the velocity
of the particle ordinary ordinary
velocity so this is DP by DT * gamma
let's see what's on the right hand side
on the right hand side we have things
like let's take this term here
q fxy
uy but uy is the same as
VY * gamma
likewise
uh likewise for all the terms uy u z and
u
z let's see um we have q
fxy
VY in other words this is going to be V
crossb
times
gamma and the last term is just electric
field times U not and U not is just
gamma from the U's here the 's are V's
time gamma and the last one here is just
gamma right okay so the gamas cancel
and guess what we get exactly what uh
what lence
had except there something slightly
different and that's that P is not M * V
but it's m * U so there is a hidden
gamma in here the relativity is hidden
in the definition of gamma we can really
write this as d by
DT not of MV
but of MV *
gamma gamma changes along the
trajectory and so gamma is not a
constant but it is DP by DT so it looks
exactly like lent with the exception
that we have to calculate p in the right
way as proper uh in terms of proper
velocity so we've we've reproduced
first line on that bottom board isn't
that a q *
Z
yeah
absolutely okay that's the that is the
lorence force law as
derived by and logic was nice the logic
was nice we first proved that the
acceleration and the velocity are
orthogonal in the four-dimensional sense
that told us that the force is
orthogonal to the
velocity the only the only simple way to
do that is to build the force out of an
anti-symmetric tensor so that when we
dot it back into the velocity we get
zero and then we just worked it out we
just worked it out making the
identifications with an older fashioned
kind of
notation this is just purely notation
the definition is here this is B this is
e when it's all put together it simply
has the simple form of a uh of a four
vector
equation because it's an equation
between four vectors on both sides it
will be the same in every reference
frame okay you call that that
math or
physics uh look once it's a bit of buck
for is there physics in there or is it
just yeah there look this there there
this's there's heavyweight physics in
there the heavyweight physics is that
the laws of nature are the are the same
in every reference
frame uh that that went in and the other
thing that went in I mean if we're doing
it you know we would really derive it
from nothing there are other Force laws
other kinds of force
laws uh
we certainly had or I certainly had in
the back of my mind that we were talking
about things with electric and magnetic
fields but
um on the other hand not very much was
used we used the idea that if an
equation is a four vector equation it's
the same in every reference frame that
was the most important thing uh other
pieces other things we used we used for
example the fact that it's a that it's a
second order differential equation
this is DX by DT so this is d2x by dt^ S
why isn't a d3x by DT squar or d4x
physics goes into
that uh there's plenty of physics that
goes into that that the equations of
motion are second order which is
equivalent to the statement but it's a
physical statement it's not a
mathematical statement that in order to
predict the future you need to know the
position and velocity of every particle
you don't need to know the acceleration
the equation gives you the acceleration
uh the equation could have been that the
derivative of the acceleration is equal
to the force and then you would also
need to know the acceleration the in the
beginning but uh physics tells you that
that's not uh experimental physics tells
you that's that's not
correct so it's a bit of both I mean
uh so if someone thought of this from
scratch just by analogy eventually have
gotten check it experimentally because
it's physics
well you can call what you want I mean
it is what it is it is what it
is let's talk about the transformation
properties of the electromagnetic field
tensor how it
transforms uh again as's a homework
assignment I can assign you to work out
the transformation properties of all of
the components of the electric and
magnetic
fields in particular the transformation
properties when you do a loren
transformation along the xais when you
have two observers moving relative to
each other along the
x-axis I could have taken the y- AIS but
it would be no different except that X
would become
y
okay the way to think about it is to
First write down the transformation law
for the product of two vectors the
simplest tensor we want to work out the
transformation laws for a tensor all
tensors transform the same
way right so if we work out the
transformation law for a simple tensor
composed of a product of two vectors
you'll see as I'll show that that tells
us everything we need to know so for
example supposing we want to know in the
primed reference frame the primed
reference frame is the one moving let's
say to the right with velocity V I'm
Prime you're unprimed okay and I move to
the
right uh let me just write down for you
to remind you the transformation laws of
the
coordinates and let's call them
X1 X1 which is what I usually call
X Prime X Prime is equal to X which is
X1 minus VT which is minus
VX / < TK of 1 - V ^
2 x not prime this is T Prime
whoops is equal to
the no is equal to
one which is equal to
x minus vx1
/ s < TK of 1 - V ^2 and what about X2
and X3 X2 X2 Prime is equal to
X2 these a y and
z this is the transformation property
for all vectors all vectors transform
the same way all right so now now let's
work out the transformation property of
a tensor let's for example take two
vectors let's make a tensor out of two
vectors A and
B right in other words a mu B new let's
concentrate on the first component of
the electric field sorry the second
component of the electric field which
one do I want
now the first component of the electric
field in the primed reference frame now
what is ex
ex is
really F
not1 Prime I'm trying to find F not one
prime assuming that I know things in the
unprimed frame now FN Prime is like I'm
going to write uh not equal but is sort
of
like the product of two
vectors A KN
B1 this would also be a component of a
tensor in fact it would be the not one
component of a tensor
so one does not mean Prime here let's
calculate a KN
B1 Prime
how do we do that well we know what a
prime is here's
how the the not component of a vector
changes we know what the one component
of the vector how it changes so all we
have to do is substitute let's
substitute what is a prime a prime is
built out of a and A1 the same way that
X Prime is built out of the components X
and X1 let's see if we can get what it
is a prime is going to be
a minus VA A1 sorry a I better put the
indices in the right place
a the
A1 / sare < TK of 1us V
^2 that's a prime now what about B1
Prime B1 Prime we have to see how the
first component of vectors change that's
going to be
B1 minus
v b not / < TK of 1 minus V ^2 does
everybody see what I've
done I've said that ex is a component of
a tensor the not one component of the
tensor just as an exercise I'm going to
calculate how a similar tensor namely a
mu B new transforms I'm going to see
what happens to the not one component of
it in the primed frame to do that all I
have to do is substitute in the not
component the prime not component that I
get from this equation over
here the one component of the primed B
that I get from this comp equation over
here that's these two factors is that
clear anybody not follow
it good all right now let's multiply
them together and see what we get
first of all we're going to get 1 / 1us
V ^2 that's the easy thing just multiply
these two together now next we get a
B1 that's a component of the of the
corresponding tensor in the unprimed
reference frame we'll use
that now we get minus
V A1 B1
minus V A
B that comes from the a b term here and
the A1 B1 term here and
finally plus v^
2 a1b
not now the only unusual thing about f
is that it's
anti-symmetric we could guess we could
guess now what the transformation
property of FN one is let let me let's
make the guess
F1
Prime is equal to
F1 that's from
here from here minus
V
f11 this is f11 minus v
f plus v
2 F1 KN that's this all
divided by 1 -
v^2 okay I've said a * B transforms as a
tensor here's its transformation
properties I know it just
straightforwardly from the
transformation properties of the two
vectors and now I identify the
components of ab with the components of
a tensor
this is how a tensor transforms but an
anti-symmetric tensor is especially
simple f11 and F not aren't there so we
can erase
them what about F1 and F1
KN they're the minus of each other so
this becomes F1 * 1 - V ^ 2
and the whole thing is just FN
one oh my goodness it looks like FN 1
Prime is the same as FN one and that's
correct what does that say that says
that if two observers are moving down
the axis and there's an electric field
along the axis
okay we're doing a loren transformation
along the one axis and we looking at the
component of the field along the one
axis it says that the component of the
field along the direction of relative
motion is
unchanged is the same and that's a true
fact that the component of electric
field and it's also true of the magnetic
field maybe we'll do it
uh it's also true of the magnetic
field in fact the electric and magnetic
field transform very similar to each
other okay but now let's do a case which
is less trivial where there is an
interesting transformation
[Applause]
law let's work out the transformation
property of a component of the electric
field perpendicular to the direction of
motion well what's the transformation of
a not we had it worked out over here the
transformation
of
prime uh the transformation of
a
is unpr a minus VA
A1 again divided > 1us V
^2 that's a prime and then
B2 this is incidentally this B here is
not the magnetic field don't get
confused this is just two vectors any
two vectors what is the transformation
property of the second component of a
vector the Y component in this case when
I transform along the
x-axis nothing changes so this is just
B2 let's see what we have we have a B2
/un of 1 - v^ 2 a
B2 over > 1 - v^ 2
well that suggests
that we replace this by
F2 / < TK of 1 - V
^2 that's the first term and then minus
V time A1 B2 that's
F12
F12 / > of 1 - V ^2
okay let's see what this says this was
the primed
component E2
Prime E2
Prime is equal this is
E2 minus V now what is
F12 F12 is plus or minus B3 which is it
I think it's B3 minus B3 I
forgot
H minus B3 so it must be plus
vb3 / > 1 - V
^2 so we see
that uh this is E2 E2 Prime
does change and it's equal to E2 plus
vb3 time
gamma if the velocity is slow then gamma
is close to one and it just
says that the electric field mixes in a
little bit the second component of the
electric field mixes in with a little
bit of the third component of the
magnetic
field this was for a transformation
along the x-axis along the one AIS you
can work out in the same way the details
of all of the transformation properties
of all of the components of the electric
and magnetic field and find out if you
know them in one frame the stationary
frame what they are in the other frame
okay uh in particular you can check that
if you have only a magnetic field in one
frame that if you move relative to it
you see an electric and the magnetic
field
uh and you can work out the direction
that the electric and the magnetic field
will point
in and these transformation properties
for the electric and magnetic field will
always be such that uh that the
equations of motion in any frame of
reference for the charged particle are
the
same
okay okay any questions about the
charged particle in the electric and
magnetic
field if you have a current flowing
through a wire you got magnetic
field what sort of velocity do you have
to go at in order to make that magnetic
field equal to
zero Zer uh
zero why to go along with with the with
with that charge if you have current in
a in a
wire and you've got Q's going at some V
Through the
Wire what what velocity do you have to
go in order to make the
sounds like you want to keep up with the
uh with the electrons yeah is it it's
probably well I don't it's not a
relativistic velocity but I mean it's
not it's it's a medium velocity yeah but
the we can work it out um we can work it
out but
uh very slow very slow no it's not that
slow to get rid of the magnetic field no
well the the velocity of electrons in a
wire is
slow yeah the drift
velocity what is it it's me/
second that's not the right velocity I'm
not sure why but uh
um moving a well well wait wait wait
wait you got to be
careful yeah yeah yeah yeah there's
positive charges there too
um no it doesn't transform that
simply uh I think we just have to work
out the magnetic field and do it that's
something I I don't know the answer to
off hand uh I suspect it's sort of
intermediate not too slow not too fast
it's not very slow can you ever get rid
of the magnetic
field
uh
something yeah I think you can get
um no
not if there's only a magnetic field not
if there's only a magnetic field you
can't get rid of it right that's that's
the problem you can but if there's an
electric field and a large electric
field you can you might be able to get
rid of the magnetic field in other words
the transformation property of the
electric field will produce a little bit
of magnetic field which could cancel the
original magnetic field if all you have
is a magnetic field to begin with no you
can't right uh but for example I mean
all right what I was thinking which was
inappropriate for the problem but if I
had a moving collection of charges and
the moving collection of charges makes a
magnetic field it also makes an electric
field if you know just a lump of charge
it's moving it makes an electric field
and it makes a magnetic field then I can
answer very quickly what velocity do I
have to move with to get rid of the
magnetic field I just have to move with
the object and there's no magnetic field
that uh the uh the current in the wire
is trickier and the electric field
cancels out from the protons and the
electrons and there's no way to get rid
of it there's no way to get rid of it
um okay does
um does the electric potential and the
and the vector potential form a four
Vector yeah very similar to form a four
Vector
uh we ALS we will also study Maxwell's
equations but before we do
um want to think a little bit about
waves scalar waves waves scalar wave
equations uh the main point
being that we we haven't talked
about derivatives of fields
we've talked about the object
DX which might be a little displacement
along a world
line now let's come to an entirely what
apparently is an entirely different
subject a theory of fields let's forget
now particles let's concentrate on
fields fields are things which vary in
SpaceTime so they depend in General on
all four components of position let's
call five f is a field five for field uh
it's a scalar field which means it has
only one component the simplest possible
thing we can
make and now we can differentiate it we
can differentiate
it to create
d by DX
mu this consists of four terms or four
components d by DX D5 by
Dy d by
DZ and finally d by
DT or D by dx1 D by dx2 D5 by dx3 and D5
by
DX they form a four Vector
but they form the covariant components
of a four
vector they transform slightly
differently than the components DX
mu how do they
transform they transform the same way
not as DX mu but as DX mu with a lower
component let me remind you what the
lower component means the lower
component simply means you change the
sign of the time components no the time
the sign of the space
components if D Super X mu is a set of
four numbers which form the
contravariant components of a vector
then this object here is just minus dx1
dot dot dot d
X3
minus also dx2 and then DX not you
change the space components and those
things Define the covariant comp
components of the vector it's the same
geometric object just being described
differently just being described in a
different
notation it's useful because we can make
scalers
by Contracting lower and upper indices
Contracting means you take a lower index
and an upper index you identify them in
sum and that makes uh uh scalers so it's
a useful device it takes into account
this extra sign
uh in things like t^2 - x^2 - y^2 -
z^2
okay if you were to work
out the transformation properties of the
derivatives now how do you do that you
know how the X's themselves transform
you know what the coordinate
Transformations are uh X1 Prime is equal
to whatever it is all that Loren
transformation stuff you know how they
transform you know what combinations of
the old coordinates the new coordinates
are and you can work out you can work
out the derivatives of the same field fi
with respect to X Prime
mu I'm not going to do that on the
Blackboard it's a little bit
tedious we could work it out and see
what the connection between the
derivatives with respect to the prime
variables the moving coordinates and the
coordinates of the unprimed coordinate
frame R and the answer is that they
transform the same way not as the DX M's
here but the DX M's with a lower
index that's fairly easy to prove and so
this object is a four Vector but it
forms the covariant components of a four
Vector these are the four Co the the um
the the covariant components of a four
Vector is it clear what that means to
everybody just that it transforms in
that way in forms of complex of four
things can we make an object with upper
components sure we can make an object
with upper components we just change the
sign of the space components and leave
the sign of the time component alone all
right so we have two sets of objects we
have
DF by DX let's call it 1 2 and
3 together with d by
DX and that's what we call D by DX
mu now we can also consider and this is
a definition
now d by DX with an upper index instead
of the lower index it now has an upper
index and that's just the same thing
here let's cross this out with a minus
sign
here in other words the object with the
lower index and the upper index are
related in the same way that all four
vectors with upper and lower components
are
related in fact every time you
differentiate an object if you have any
tensor or any vector vector or any
scalar and you differentiate
it let's suppose you take a vector field
here's some Vector field that depends on
X let's suppose it has an upper index
for Simplicity and you differentiate
it with respect to X
new that makes a tensor but it makes a
tensor with one upper
index and one lower index every time the
derivative operator acts it simply puts
another index on the object all right so
if V is a vector and you differentiate
it you get a tensor if V is a tensor and
you differentiate it you get an object
with yet another index and so forth the
differentiation always puts the index
downstairs right so differentiation is
another rule that allows you to form
vectors vectors
tensors uh and so
forth now what I want to discuss for the
remaining time
today is wave equations and the
invariance of wave equations the
invariance of wave equations follows if
the wave equation has the form that some
scalar is equal to
zero scalars are the same in every
reference
frame and so if we can write the
equation for some wave in the form a
scalar is equal to zero then we can be
sure it's the same in every reference
frame in other words if we coordinate
transform things let's uh try to do that
wave equations by their very nature
incidentally always have two derivatives
not one derivative they correspond to
Second derivatives acting on uh on
fields of course we could imagine wave
equations with uh six derivatives but
the simplest wave equations Maxwell's
equations other wave equations have
second derivatives in them that means
that we going to have a derivative and
another derivative acting on some field
equals zero this is a typical example of
a wave equation there are other wave
equations but let's uh let's look for
one like that we want it to be the same
in every reference frame so that means
we want it to be the left hand side to
be a
Scala left hand side to be a Scala would
be a a one way of going to make a wave
equation a single wave equation right
there's only one way to do it there's
really only one way to do it and that's
we've got to begin by differentiating so
let's put me there the only way to make
a scaler out of this is to
differentiate
again and to put the index here upstairs
what does it mean that the index here is
upstairs it means that the space
components of the derivative
are treated with a negative sign this is
the simplest wave equation it's
invariant because whenever you contract
a lower index with an upper index it
automatically gives you something which
is invariant under Loren Transformations
so this is the simplest example of a
wave equation and let's write out what
it actually
means let's write out what it actually
means in
detail
uh let's take first the time component
the time component is just
DFI and now the time components don't
change sign when you raise the index so
this is just the second
derivative the second derivative with
respect to
time the first derivatives do change
sign when you raise an index and so this
is minus
DC sorry DC 5
by dx2 same thing for
[Music]
y^2 same thing for
z^2 this equation well this is d by dt^
2 this equation has the um the virtue of
being the same in every reference frame
how do you check it you write it in a
form in which it's manifestly just a
scalar one index upstairs one index
downstairs okay that always gives you a
scaler that's the simplest wave equation
the reason I'm writing it down now is
because we want to get to Maxwell's
equations this is an example of a simple
wave equation Maxwell's wave equations
are more more complicated but we want to
get to Maxwell's equations and we want
to write them in a form which is equally
manifestly Lenin variant that's our goal
we're not going to do that tonight I
think we're going to quit now next time
we'll come back and work out Maxwell's
equations in a covariant
notation they're equations which mix up
electric and magnetic fields in a
somewhat uh intricate way but they have
the virtue of being written or the way
we write them has the virtue of being
explicitly Lenin variant I'm getting
tired so I think we'll quit
uh any questions rather Conant what's
that why is the scal beal to Z oh it
could be no it could be a constant in
fact it could be any number of things it
could be any scalar on the right hand
side this is one particular example of a
wave equation another one which is
interesting is to write a constant here
times F all right what's on the right
hand side you could have constant time
5^ squ you could have all kinds of
things uh the simple equation is just to
have zero and we're going to discuss
those equations we're going to work them
out we're going to work them out study
their
Solutions understand how they behave but
this is just the simplest example of a
wave equation and next time we'll uh
we'll study them in some
[Music]
detail the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at Stanford EDU